<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
 <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>

<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="std"
     docName="draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-prefixlist-02"
     ipr="trust200902"
     xml:lang="en"
     sortRefs="true"
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="true"
     version="3">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="RPKI Signed Prefix List">
      A profile for Signed Prefix Lists for Use in the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)
    </title>

    <author fullname="Job Snijders" initials="J." surname="Snijders">
      <organization>Fastly</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <code/>
          <city>Amsterdam</city>
          <country>Netherlands</country>
        </postal>
        <email>job@fastly.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Geoff Huston" initials="G." surname="Huston">
      <organization>APNIC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6 Cordelia St</street>
          <code>QLD 4101</code>
          <city>South Brisbane</city>
          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>
        <email>gih@apnic.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <area>ops</area>
    <workgroup>sidrops</workgroup>

    <keyword>security</keyword>
    <keyword>cryptography</keyword>
    <keyword>X.509</keyword>

    <abstract>

      <t>
         This document defines a "Signed Prefix List", a Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS) protected content type for use with the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) to carry the complete list of prefixes which an Autonomous System (AS) may originate to all or any of its routing peers.
         The validation of a Signed Prefix List confirms that the holder of the listed ASN produced the object, and that this list is a current, accurate and complete description of address prefixes that may be announced into the routing system originated by this AS.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        This document defines a "Signed Prefix List", a Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS) <xref target="RFC5652"/> <xref target="RFC6268"/> protected content type to carry a list of IP address prefixes and an Autonomous System Number.
        The list of prefixes describes the maximal set of prefixes that the Autonomous System MAY announce to any of its routing peers.
        The content is signed by the holder of the RPKI private key associated with the listed ASN.
      </t>
      <t>
        RPKI Signed Prefix Lists allow other RPKI-validating remote routing entities to audit the collection of announcements that have the subject ASN as the originating AS.
        Any prefixes originated by this AS not contained in a validated Signed Prefix List <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be regarded as ineligible, but ultimately their consequent handling by the local routing entity that performed the audit function is a matter of local policy.
      </t>
      <t>
        The intent of this object is to offer a RPKI-based successor to the <xref target="RFC2622"/> 'route-set' class objects used in Internet Routing Registries (IRRs).
        The semantics of the route-set and the Signed Prefix List are similair.
        The difference is that the RPKI signature allows a relying party of be assured of the currency and authenticity of the Signed Prefix List as a complete enumeration of all prefixes that may be announced as originating by this AS if the object can be validated by the RPKI.
      </t>
      <t>
        Signed Prefix List objects follow the Signed Object Template for the RPKI <xref target="RFC6488"/>.
      </t>

      <section anchor="requirements">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
          The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>The Signed Prefix List ContentType</name>
      <t>
        The eContentType for a Prefix List is defined as id-ct-rpkiSignedPrefixList, with Object Identifier (OID) 1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.1.51.
      </t>
      <t>
        This OID <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> appear within both the eContentType in the encapContentInfo object and the ContentType signed attribute in the signerInfo object (see <xref target="RFC6488"/>).
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="econtent">
      <name>The Signed Prefix List eContent</name>
      <t>
        The content of a Signed Prefix List is a single ASN and a list of IP address prefixes.
        An Signed Prefix List is formally defined as follows:
      </t>

      <sourcecode anchor="ASN.1" type="asn.1" src="RpkiSignedPrefixList-2024.asn"/>

      <section>
        <name>Version</name>
        <t>
          The version number of the RpkiSignedPrefixList <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 0.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>asID</name>
        <t>
          The Autonomous System Number contained here <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a contained within the set of AS Identifier resources listed by the EE certificate carried in the CMS certificates field.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>prefixBlocks</name>
        <t>
          This field contains a SEQUENCE of AddressFamilyAddressPrefixes.
          The AddressFamilyAddressPrefixes elements <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ordered in ascending order by numeric value of the addressFamily field.
        </t>
        <section>
          <name>Element AddressFamilyAddressPrefixes</name>
          <t>
            This field contains a SEQUENCE which contains one instance of addressFamily and one instance of addressPrefixes.
          </t>
          <section>
            <name>addressFamily</name>
            <t>
              This field contains a OCTET STRING which is either '0001'H (IPv4) or '0002'H (IPv6).
            </t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>addressPrefixes</name>
            <t>
              This field contains a SEQUENCE of parameterized AddressPrefix instances.
            </t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>Element AddressPrefix</name>
            <t>
              This element is length bounded through the Information Object Class ADDRESS-FAMILY.
              The type is a BIT STRING, see <xref target="RFC3779" section="2.2.3.8"/> for more information on encoding IP prefixes.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <name>Canonical form for prefixBlocks</name>
            <t>
              As the data structure described by the SignedPrefixList <xref target="ASN.1"/> module allows for many different ways to represent the same set of IP address prefix information, a canonical form is defined such that every set of address prefixes has a unique representation.
              In order to produce and verify this canonical form, the process described in this section <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used to ensure information elements are unique with respect to one another and sorted in ascending order.
              This canonicalization procedure builds upon the canonicalization procedure specified in section 2.2.3.6 of <xref target="RFC3779"/> and <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidrops-rfc6482bis" section="4.3.3"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
              In order to semantically compare, sort, and deduplicate the contents of the prefixBlocks field, each AddressPrefix element is mapped to an abstract data element composed of three integer values:
            </t>
            <dl>
              <dt>afi</dt>  <dd>The AFI value appearing in the addressFamily field of the containing addressPrefixes as an integer.</dd>
              <dt>addr</dt> <dd>The first IP address of the IP prefix appearing in the AddressPrefix field, as a 32-bit (IPv4) or 128-bit (IPv6) integer value.</dd>
              <dt>plen</dt> <dd>The prefix length of the IP prefix appearing in the AddressPrefix address field as an integer value.</dd>
            </dl>
            <t>
              Thus, the equality or relative order of two AddressPrefix elements can be tested by comparing their abstract representations.
            </t>
            <section>
              <name>Comparator</name>
              <t>
                The set of prefixBlocks is totally ordered.
                The order of two prefixBlocks is determined by the first non-equal comparison in the following list.
              </t>
              <ol>
                <li>
                  Data elements with a lower afi value precede data elements with a higher afi value.
                </li>
                <li>
                  Data elements with a lower addr value precede data elements with a higher addr value.
                </li>
                <li>
                  Data elements with a lower plen value precede data elements with a higher plen value.
                </li>
              </ol>
              <t>
                Data elements for which all three values compare equal are duplicates of one another.
              </t>
            </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="validation">
      <name>Signed Prefix List Validation</name>
      <t>
        To validate a Signed Prefix List, the RP <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> perform all the validation checks specified in <xref target="RFC6488"/>.
        In addition, the RP <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> perform the following validation steps:
      </t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          The contents of the CMS eContent field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> conform to all of the constraints described in <xref target="econtent"/>.
        </li>
        <li>
          The Autonomous System Identifier Delegation extension <xref target="RFC3779"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be present in the EE certificate contained in the CMS certificates field.
        </li>
        <li>
          The AS identifier present in the RpkiSignedPrefixList eContent 'asID' field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a subset of the AS Indentifiers present in the certificate extension.
        </li>
        <li>
          The Autonomous System Identifier Delegation extension <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain "inherit" elements.
        </li>
        <li>
          The IP Address Delegation Extension <xref target="RFC3779"/> is not used in Signed Prefix List, and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be present in the EE certificate.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <t>
        Multiple valid Signed Prefix List objects which contain the same asID could exist.
        In such cases the union of address prefix members forms the complete set of members.
        It is highly <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that a compliant CA maintains a single Signed Prefix List for a given asID.
      </t>
      <t>
        If an AS holder publishes a Signed Prefix List, then relying parties <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> assume that the list is complete for that originating AS, and the presence of any route with the same AS as the originating AS and an address prefix that is not included in the Signed Prefix List implies that the route has been propagated within the routing system without the permission of the originating AS.
      </t>
      <t>
        The construction of an 'allowlist' for a given EBGP session using Signed Prefix List(s) compliments both best current practises <xref target="RFC7454"/> and the practise of rejecting RPKI-ROV-invalid BGP route announcements <xref target="RFC6811"/>.
        In other words, if a given BGP route is covered by a Signed Prefix List, but also is "invalid" from a Route Origin Validation perspective, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> to reject the route announcement.
      </t>

      <section title="EE Certificates">
        <t>
          The Certificate Authority (CA) <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> sign only one Signed Prefix List with each generated private key and <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> generate a new key pair for each new version of a Signed Prefix List object.
          The CA <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> generate a new End Entity (EE) certificate for each signing of a particular Signed Prefix List.
          An associated EE certificate used in this fashion is termed a "one-time-use" EE certificate (see <xref target="RFC6487" section="3"/>).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Object Filenames">
        <t>
          A guideline for naming Signed Prefix List objects is that the file name chosen in the repository be a value derived from the public key of the EE certificate.
          One such method of generating a publication name is described in <xref target="RFC4387" section="2.1"/>; convert the 160-bit hash of a EE's public key value into a 27-character string using a modified form of Base64 encoding, with an additional modification as proposed in Section 5, table 2, of <xref target="RFC4648"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        Relying Parties are warned that the data in a Signed Prefix List is self-asserted by the AS holder.
        There is no implied authority from any IP prefix holder that grants the AS permission to originate a route for any prefixes.
        Such an authority is separately conveyed in the RPKI as a ROA.
      </t>
      <t>
        While a one-time-use EE certificate must only be used to generate and sign a single Signed Prefix List object, CAs are not technically restricted from generating and signing multiple different Signed Prefix List objects with a single key pair.
        Any Signed Prefix List objects sharing the same EE certificate cannot be revoked individually.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>

      <section>
        <name>SMI Security for S/MIME CMS Content Type (1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.1)</name>
        <t>
          IANA has temporarily allocated the following in the "SMI Security for S/MIME CMS Content Type (1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.1)" registry:
        </t>

        <table anchor="cms-content-type" align="center">
          <name></name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decimal</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th>
            </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>51</td>
                <td>id-ct-rpkiSignedPrefixList</td>
                <td>draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-prefixlist</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>RPKI Signed Objects</name>
        <t>
          IANA is requested to register the following OID in the "RPKI Signed Objects" registry <xref target="RFC6488"/>:
        </t>

        <table anchor="rpki-signed-prefixlist" align="center">
          <name></name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OID</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
            </tr>
        </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>Signed Prefix List</td>
              <td>1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.1.51</td>
              <td>draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-prefixlist</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>RPKI Repository Name Schemes</name>
        <t>
          IANA is requested to add the Signed Prefix List file extension to the "RPKI Repository Name Schemes" registry <xref target="RFC6481"/> as follows:
        </t>

        <table anchor="rpki-repository-name-schemes" align="center">
          <name></name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filename Extension</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RPKI Object</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
            </tr>
        </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>.spl</td>
              <td>Signed Prefix List</td>
              <td>draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-prefixlist</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>SMI Security for S/MIME Module Identifier (1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.0)</name>
        <t>
          IANA is requested to allocate the following in the "SMI Security for S/MIME Module Identifier (1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.0)" registry:
        </t>

        <table anchor="smi-security-identifier" align="center">
          <name></name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decimal</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>TBD</td>
              <td>id-mod-rpkiSignedPrefixList-2024</td>
              <td>draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-prefixlist</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>Media Types</name>
        <t>
          IANA is requested to register the media type "application/rpki-prefixlist" in the "Media Types" registry as follows:
        </t>
        <section>
        <name>Signed Prefix List Media Type</name>
        <dl spacing="compact">
           <dt>Type name:</dt><dd>application</dd>
           <dt>Subtype name:</dt><dd>rpki-prefixlist</dd>
           <dt>Required parameters:</dt><dd>N/A</dd>
           <dt>Optional parameters:</dt><dd>N/A</dd>
           <dt>Encoding considerations:</dt><dd>binary</dd>
           <dt>Security considerations:</dt><dd>Carries a Signed Prefix List. This media type contains no active content. See <xref target="validation"/> of draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-prefixlist for further information.</dd>
           <dt>Interoperability considerations:</dt><dd>N/A</dd>
           <dt>Published specification:</dt><dd>draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-prefixlist</dd>
           <dt>Applications that use this media type:</dt><dd>RPKI operators</dd>
           <dt>Fragment identifier considerations:</dt><dd>N/A</dd>
           <dt>Additional information:</dt>
           <dd>
           <dl spacing="compact">
             <dt><br/></dt><dd/>
             <dt>Content:</dt><dd>This media type is a signed object, as defined in [RFC6488], which contains a list of prefixes as defined in draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-prefixlist.</dd>
             <dt>Magic number(s):</dt><dd>N/A</dd>
             <dt>File extension(s):</dt><dd>.spl</dd>
             <dt>Macintosh file type code(s):</dt><dd>N/A</dd>
           </dl>
           </dd>
           <dt>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:</dt><dd>Job Snijders (job@fastly.com)</dd>
           <dt>Intended usage:</dt><dd>COMMON</dd>
           <dt>Restrictions on usage:</dt><dd>N/A</dd>
           <dt>Author:</dt><dd>Job Snijders (job@fastly.com)</dd>
           <dt>Change controller:</dt><dd>IETF</dd>
        </dl>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

          <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2622.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3779.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5652.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6481.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6487.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6488.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-ietf-sidrops-rfc6482bis.xml"/>
      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

       <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4387.xml"/>
       <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml"/>
       <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6268.xml"/>
       <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6811.xml"/>
       <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7454.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="rpki-client" target="https://www.rpki-client.org/">
          <front>
            <title>rpki-client</title>
            <author fullname="Claudio Jeker"/>
            <author fullname="Kristaps Dzonsons"/>
            <author fullname="Theo Buehler"/>
            <author fullname="Job Snijders"/>
            <date month="February" year="2024" />
          </front>
        </reference>

      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="acknowledgements">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>
        The authors wish to thank
        <contact fullname="Russ Housley"/>
        and
        <contact fullname="Theo Buehler"/>
        for feedback.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Example payloads</name>

    <section anchor="example-prefixlist">
      <name>Example Signed Prefix List eContent Payload</name>
      <t>
        Below an example of a DER-encoded Signed Prefix List eContent is provided with annotation following the '#' character.
      </t>
      <artwork>
<![CDATA[
$ cat << EOF | xxd -r -ps | openssl asn1parse -inform DER -i -dump
3081b102023cca3081aa307304020001306d03040043ddf5030400a5fee1
030506a5feff00030400c093a8030400c22047030400c63a03030401cc02
1e030400d11800030400d11801030400d11803030402d11804030403d118
08030400d11808030400d11809030404d11810030405d11820030406d118
40030407d11880303304020002302d03070120010418144e030700200106
7c208c030700200107fbfd040307002607fae002450307002a0eb2400000
EOF
    0:d=0  hl=3 l= 177 cons: SEQUENCE
    3:d=1  hl=2 l=   2 prim:  INTEGER       :3CCA  # AS 15562
    7:d=1  hl=3 l= 170 cons:  SEQUENCE
   10:d=2  hl=2 l= 115 cons:   SEQUENCE
   12:d=3  hl=2 l=   2 prim:    OCTET STRING
      0000 - 00 01                                 # AFI IPv4
   16:d=3  hl=2 l= 109 cons:    SEQUENCE
   18:d=4  hl=2 l=   4 prim:     BIT STRING
      0000 - 00 43 dd f5                           # 67.221.245.0/24
   24:d=4  hl=2 l=   4 prim:     BIT STRING
      0000 - 00 a5 fe e1                           # 165.254.225.0/24
   30:d=4  hl=2 l=   5 prim:     BIT STRING
      0000 - 06 a5 fe ff                           # 165.254.255.0/26
      0005 - <SPACES/NULS>
... snip ...
  127:d=2  hl=2 l=  51 cons:   SEQUENCE
  129:d=3  hl=2 l=   2 prim:    OCTET STRING
      0000 - 00 02                                 # AFI IPv6
  133:d=3  hl=2 l=  45 cons:    SEQUENCE
  135:d=4  hl=2 l=   7 prim:     BIT STRING
      0000 - 01 20 01 04 18 14 4e                  # 2001:418:144e::/47
  144:d=4  hl=2 l=   7 prim:     BIT STRING
      0000 - 00 20 01 06 7c 20 8c                  # 2001:67c:208c::/48
... snip ...
]]>
      </artwork>

    </section>

    </section>

<!--
    <section removeInRFC="true">
      <name>Implementation status</name>
      <t>
        This section records the status of known implementations of the protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in RFC 7942.
        The description of implementations in this section is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing drafts to RFCs.
        Please note that the listing of any individual implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF.
        Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the information presented here that was supplied by IETF contributors.
        This is not intended as, and must not be construed to be, a catalog of available implementations or their features.
        Readers are advised to note that other implementations may exist.
      </t>
      <t>
        According to RFC 7942, "this will allow reviewers and working groups to assign due consideration to documents that have the benefit of running code, which may serve as evidence of valuable experimentation and feedback that have made the implemented protocols more mature.
        It is up to the individual working groups to use this information as they see fit".
      </t>

      <ul>
        <li>
          Example .spl files were created by Job Snijders.
        </li>
        <li>
          A validator implementation <xref target="rpki-client"/>, written in C was provided by Job Snijders from Fastly.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
-->

  </back>

</rfc>
